ILGWU Archives Department, Robert Lazar Papers 5780/121
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Archives Department, Robert Lazar Papers
1890-1985
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Lazar, Robert
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/121
4.33 cubic feet
4.3 linear ft.
Records (documents).
In addition to documentation of the archives' everyday operation, the papers of ILGWU archivist Robert Lazar include photocopies of materials from the ILGWU records, collected printed material about the ILGWU, sheet music, meeting minutes of local unions, and accounting ledgers.
5516837
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
P. Leary, August 07, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 15, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The ILGWU Archives were established in New York City in 1973, under the direction of Henoch Mendelsund. Robert Lazar served as archivist. The archives sought to collect union correspondence, meeting minutes, collective bargaining agreements, publications, photographs, audio recordings, film, and memorabilia. In 1987, the ILGWU Archives were transferred to the Kheel Center.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Archives Department include administrative records files relating to the establishment and operation of the unit, subject files containing photocopies of archival material, archival records maintained by the department, and publications.
Administrative records document how the archive was built, operated, and used. They include inventory and accession forms, correspondence with union officials and donors, financial records, and guidelines for the processing and care of archival records. These also include procedures for using the collections, guidelines for donating materials, and signed forms by researchers who accessed the archives. Materials relating to the archives' oral history project are also contained in these administrative files. These oral history audio recordings and transcripts (5780 OH and 5780/110 OHT) are available at the Kheel Center.
Subject files include prominent figures in the union, local unions, and other ILGWU affiliates and contain photocopies of records documenting the work of these individuals and organizations. Among the subject files and archival records are the ILGWU's founding meeting minutes (5780/111, box 1, folder 13), as well as minutes of the ILGWU predecessor union Sanctuary Local Assembly 3038 of the Knights of Labor.
Archival records include union correspondence, accounting ledgers, local union meeting minutes, and other material. The accounting ledgers of the Central States region are among the relatively few records held at the Kheel Center that document the activities of that department. The meeting minutes of Local 89, Local 48, Local 414, and Local 2585/414 fill out gaps in other series. These records from the Archives Department complement those in other series of the ILGWU Records
The Archives Department Publications (5780/121 PUBS) consist of printed material collected by the unit. They include newsletters and newspapers from local unions, collective bargaining agreements, membership censuses, financial and statistical reports, information welfare funds, legal records, and some material related to arbitration. Included in the papers of longtime ILGWU Archivist Robert Lazar (5780/121) is published sheet music.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Lazar, Robert
5516837
- Schoenwald: Labor Studies Center -- Retirement Planning, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Schoenwald: Friendly Visitors Program (Office for the Aging), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Schoenwald: Office for the Aging (Governor's Advisory Committee), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Aging: White House Conference on Aging -- Correspondence and Surveys, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Aging: White House Conference on Aging -- Articles (Clippings), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Social Security: Bert Seidman -- Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Social Security: Hearings of the Select Committee on Aging (Shoenwald), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Schneider, Ed: Correspondence, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- ILGWU Retirees Membership Meeting, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Civil Rights Complaint Against ILGWU, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Daily Labor Report and Miscellaneous Legal Updates, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Local 89 (Dressmakers Union): Executive Board Minutes, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Local 89 (Italian Dressmakers Union): Executive Board Minutes, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Scope and Contents
  Bound volume
- Local 89 (Dress and Waistmakers' Union): Summer Colony Minutes and Audit, 1923-1927 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Local 2585/414: Minutes, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Local 414: Minutes, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Local 414: Minutes, 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Local 48: Executive Board Minutes, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Appeal Committee, ILGWU: Hearings re Charges Against Local 9, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Dress Code Authority: Minutes, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Dubinsky: Gov. Cuomo Citation, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Biflex Foundations: Agreement with ILGWU, Corset and Brassiere Workers of NY Local 32 and Amalgamated Ladies' Garment Cutters' Union Local 10, 1954- 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Sophie R. Quinn Scholarship Fund, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Walterboro Dress Corp. (William Baliush, President): Promissory Note to ILGWU Revolving Fund, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Wind 'n' Sky (Saul Weinstein): Promissory Note to ILGWU Southeast Region, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- YIVO Institute for Jewish Research, Inc.: Mortgage Note with ILGWU, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Mortgage Loans, Georgia, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- One-Ninety Corporation: Articles of Incorporation, By-Laws, Stock (Knit Goods Workers Union, Local 190, Philadelphia), 1960-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- One-Ninety Corporation: Tax Exemption Letter, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- One-Ninety Corporation: Tax Returns (Form 990), 1965-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Arbitration Awards: Cases Heard by Raymond V. Ingersoll, 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Arbitration Awards: Cases Heard by Arthur S. Meyer, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Arbitration Awards: Cases Heard by Harry Hopkins, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- ILGWU Local 25, Dress and Waist Manufacturers' Association: Conference, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- ILGWU, Cloak, Suit and Skirt Manufacturers' Protective Association, NY Joint Board of Cloak and Skirt Makers' Union: Council of Conciliation Findings and Recommendations, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Joint Board of Cloak, Skirt and Reefer Makers' Union of Greater NY: Correspondence, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Industrial Council of Cloak, Skirt, and Suit Manufacturers: Legal Briefs, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  brittle
- Los Angeles Cloak Joint Board, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Amphenol-Borg (Delavan and Jefferson) Agreements/Negotiations, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Borg Textiles: Bunker-Ramos Corporation (Delavan and Jefferson) -- Negotiations and Agreement, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- H. W. Gossard: Agreement with ILGWU, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Wausau: Marathon Rubber Products -- Negotiations, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Wausau: Negotiations, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Wausau: Local 374 -- NLRB Election -- Correspondence and Contract Notes, 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Central States Region: Meyer Perlstein (ILGWU Vice President) -- Correspondence, 1937-1951 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Central States Region: Agreements and Cases, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Central States Region (Chicago): Agreement, Injunction, 1890-1924 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Unity House/Pike County Hotels Corporation: Dining Room Salaries, Income Statement, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Unity House/Pike County Hotels Corporation: Financial Reports, 1937-1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Unity House: Tax-Exempt Status, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Grossinger's and Local 1 Dining Room Employees, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Unity Broadcasting Corporation of Massachusetts: Stock Certificates, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Union Dues, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- 50th Anniversary: Local 178, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- All American Fashion Show, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Chaikin 10th Anniversary Invitations, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Affiliated Dress Manufacturers: Agreement, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Affiliated Dress Manufacturing: Agreement, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Liberal Party Primary: Gus Tyler, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Liberal Party Primary: Javits, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Liberal Party Primary: Johnson, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Liberal Party Primary: Republican-Liberal Collaboration Scandal -- Newspaper Clippings, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Liberal Party Primary: Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Local 10: 1968 Election (Box 3, Folder 11)
- ILGWU: Newspaper Clippings, 1975-1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- ILGWU: Convention and Election, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- ILGWU: Convention and Election, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Meyer London Biography Manuscript by Marx Lewis, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- National Maritime Union Election, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Trade Union Advisory Committee on International Affairs: German Trade Unions, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Union Labor Life Insurance Company, 1961-1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Union Health Center: 50th Anniversary Commemorative Medal (JFK), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Education Department: Training for Trade Union Service Course, 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Venezuela Labor Mission and Exhibition, "Unions In Action", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Progressive Dressmakers Workmen's Circle Branch 122: Scrapbook, 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Some material in Hebrew alphabet
- Union Label, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  sheet music
- Have a Heart, Taft-Hartley, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Men Awake!, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- I Hear America Singing, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Cradle Song (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Af a Fule Voch (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Cavalleria Rusticana (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Di Shvue (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Four Russian Folk Songs (Box 4, Folder 9)
- It's a Grand Night for Singing: Williamson Music, Inc., Choral Series, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Jota (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Les Millions D'Arlequin (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Lustspiel Overture (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Minuett from G Minor Symphony (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Orientale (Box 4, Folder 15)
- March of the Sardar (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Romanza Andaluza (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Sarabande and Gavotte (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Serenade D'Autrefois (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Serenade in Four Movements (Eine Kleine Nachtmusik) (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Slavonic Dance (Box 4, Folder 21)
- S'Loifen S'Yogen (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Transcriptions for Mandolin Orchestra (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Titus (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Bach: Aria and Minuet (Box 4, Folder 25)
  sheet music for second mandolin
- Bach: First Mandolin (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Gopak (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Gopak Complete (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Slave March (Tschaikowsky) (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Hungarian Dance No. 5 (Brahms) (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Symphony No. 6 Surprise and Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Prelude in G Minor and Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Anitra's Dance (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Minuet in G (Beethoven) (Box 4, Folder 34)
- The Nightingale (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Aria and Minuet (Bach) (Box 4, Folder 36)
- National School Orchestra: On the Volga and Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Schirmer's Band Music: Second Hungarian Rhapsody and Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Festival Fantasy, Cielito Lindo (Paparello) (Box 4, Folder 39)
- La Golondrina and Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Prelude (Rachmaninoff) (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Marche Militaire, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Largo, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Accounting Ledgers: Central States (book 1), 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Brittle, bound; oversized box
- Accounting Ledgers: Central States (book 2), 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 2)